Norman Corwin Papers
Norman Corwin Papers
- Productions of Corwin
  - Addresses
    - Nobel Committee dinner, December 10, 1945
      Corwin was introduced by Senator William J. Fulbright. Also on the speaking program were Albert Einstein, Dr. A. H. Atkinson, Richard de Rochemont, and Senator Fulbright. Speeches of all five are contained on these discs. Because of imperfect recording, at too slow a speed, the pitch of each speaker's voice is raised slightly above normal. Believed only recorded copy of these speeches extant.
      - Address to Dinner of Nobel Committee #1-2 [disc 1 of 5], December 10, 1945; corwin_0328; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Address to Dinner of Nobel Committee #3-4 [disc 2 of 5], December 10, 1945; corwin_0329; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Address to Dinner of Nobel Committee #5-6 [disc 3 of 5], December 10, 1945; corwin_0330; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Address to Dinner of Nobel Committee #17-18 [disc 4 of 5], December 10, 1945; corwin_0331; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Address to Dinner of Nobel Committee #19 [disc 5 of 5], December 10, 1945; corwin_0332; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - Sticks, Stones and Critics (197), 1966; article by Corwin (Box 9)
    - Untitled, for President Franklin D. Roosevelt (58), undated; notes written at request of Morris Ernst for use in an address by FDR; not known if it was ever used (Box 9)
    - Untitled, on The New Biology (192), 1966; manuscript by Corwin; draft, typescript, original and handwritten notes (Box 9)
  - Articles
    - Christmas: Atomic Age, Collier's (317), 1945; drafts; published version; correspondence (Oversize 1)
    - The Grand Evasion (482), circa 1968; never published, intended as newspaper article on the negelct of public service by radio and television in Southern California; research material, notes, drafts (Box 9)
    - Feature articles for Springfield [Massachusetts] Reporter (178), 1939-1945; written while Corwin was on city staff (Box 9)
    - Life and Times of "26 by Corwin," New York Times (300), 1941; fragments of typescript (Box 9)
    - New York vs Los Angeles: De-escalation in 1969? Los Angeles Times (316), draft, published version, letters to editor regarding (Box 9)
    - Sandburg in Glendora (228), 1966-1968; speech at dedication of Sandburg School in Glendora, Illinois, published in special edition of Lincoln Herald; drafts, final text, published version of speech as well as correspondence with Lincoln Herald and principal of school (Box 9)
    - Speculation on Speculation (436), 1969; article written for KCET; draft, published version (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, A-M, 1939-1961 (Box 9)
      Both of and out of this world Perfect Home, Nov 1961
      Careers in screen and radio Theatre Arts, Jul 1941
      Conscience doth make tigers Mademoiselle, Oct 1944
      Frankenstein phobia world's greatest peril The A.B.C. Weekly, 23 Feb 1947
      I can be had Theatre Arts, Jun [no year]
      Looking for art, bub! Theatre Arts, May 1947
      Mind you, I love radio Stage, Feb 1941
      Miss Hogan, take a poem TAC Magazine, Dec 1939
    - Miscellaneous, O-S, untitled, 1939-1961 (Box 9)
      O tempora! O mores! O Shapiro! Script, Sep 1947
      Of life and lenses U.S. Camera, Apr 1949
      On a note of triumph (condensation) Coronet, Aug 1945
      On a note of triumph (excerpt) Ammunition, Jun 1945
      On a note of triumph Senior Scholastic, 17 Sep 1945
      One world or none New Zealand Listener, 25 Oct 1946
      Radio drama: Samson Theatre Arts, Sep 1942
      Radio writing, USA The Writer, Feb 1951
      Script of Norman Corwin's 'Untitled' PM Daily, 31 May 1944
      Set your clock at U235 New York Herald Tribune, 4 Nov 1945
      The sovereign word: Some notes on radio drama Theatre Arts, Feb 1940
      [poem, untitled] Ohio State University Monthly, Mar 1946
  - Books
    - Challenge of Hate, by A. R. Lerner, foreword by Corwin
      - Published edition (220), 1946 (Box 10)
    - Dog in the Sky, based on radio play The Odyssey of Runyon Jones
      - Original typescript with annotations (207) (Box 10)
      - Publisher's typescript with annotations (208) (Box 10)
    - More By Corwin: Sixteen Radio Dramas (80)
      - Published edition, Henry Holt, 1944; introduction by Clifton Fadiman; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
    - On a Note of Triumph
      - Swedish translation by Erik Lindgren [MISSING 3/24/13], 1945
    - The Plot to Overthrow Christmas: A Holiday Play
      See also Productions of Corwin: Radio programs, individual: The Plot to Overthrow Christmas and Productions of others: The Congo / The Plot to Overthrow Christmas / Mood Indigo.
      - Published edition, Peter Pauper (29), 1940; privately published, only 150 copies printed; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
      - Published edition, Henry Holt, 1952; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
    - They Fly Through the Air
      - Published edition (79), 1939; drawings by Hungarian artist Laszlo Matulay; published by Vrest Orton, Weston, Vermont; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
      - Typescript, galleys (333), 1939 (Box 10)
    - Thirteen By Corwin, See Radio programs: Thirteen by Corwin.
    - Untitled and Other Radio Dramas (81)
      - Published edition (81), 1945; 1947; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
    - The World of Carl Sandburg
      - Part I (2, 4), 1960-1961; incomplete original typescript, galleys (Box 10)
      - Part II (2), 1960-1961; incomplete typescript with handwritten annotations by author (Box 11)
      - Book reviews (11), 1961; photocopies (Box 11)
      - Correspondence regarding Harcourt, Brace and World Edition (3), 1961 (Box 11)
      - Correspondence regarding Samuel French Acting Edition (5), 1960-1961 (Box 11)
  - Cinema films
    - Hedda Gabler
      - Typescript (109), 1953; final original typescript (Box 11)
    - How the West Was Won
      - Script, partial (72), 1962; memorandum; carbon of script (narration only) (Box 11)
    - The Human Family, 1950
      - Screenplay, first draft (Box 12)
      - Research material, 1948-1950; 3 folders (Box 12)
    - The King Must Die
      - Script (136), 1961; screenplay; first draft, 2 copies; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - The Last Days of James Dean
      - Typescript (63), before 1963; original typescript (Box 11)
    - Lust for Life (includes 42, 43, 44, 45, 47, 48)
      - Congratulations, 1956-1957 (Box 13)
      - Outline, early drafts (42), 1955; 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Internal memos, 1955-1956 (Box 13)
      - Lists of artwork, 1955 (Box 13)
      - Reviews, 1956-1957; newspaper and magazine; also includes ticket stub from opening night, press preview, and published "thank you" notice from Corwin (Box 13)
      - Shooting script (43), 1955; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Raquel, based on novel by Lion Feuchtwanger
      - Published copy of book, with Corwin's annotations (110-A), 1954-1956; working copy (Box 13)
      - Script (110), 1956; incomplete typescript, carbon; includes some internal memos (Box 14)
    - Scandal at Scourie, working title: "My Mother and Mr. McChesney"
      - Correspondence (111), 1952; internal memos, legal correspondence about names, etc. (Box 14)
      - Script (111), 1952; final typescript (Box 14)
    - The Story of Ruth
      - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 14)
      - Original screenplay (325), 1959 (Box 14)
      - Publicity (185, 326), 1960; press clippings, studio publicity, advertisements, reviews, etc.; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - They Ran for Their Lives
      - Scripts, 1957; screenplay, second draft (Box 14)
  - Concerts
    - Celebration of the First Anniversary of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights
      Concert at Carnegie Hall, New York City. Planned, produced and directed by Corwin for the United Nations Radio; simulcast on radio and television over NBC from Carnegie Hall (first telecast ever from Carnegie Hall). For this occasion, Corwin, acting in behalf of UN Radio, commissioned Aaron Copland to write a musical setting for the Preamble to the Declaration of Rights. This wa read by Sir laurence Olivier, who flew over from England expressly for the concert. The work was performed by the Boston Symphony Orchestra under the direction of Leonard Bernstein. Other participants in the program included Yehudi Menuhin, Nan Merriman, the Collegiate Chorale, Mrs. Franklin D. Roosevelt, Brig. Gen. Carlos P. Romulo, Secretary General Trygve Lie of the United Nations.
      - Celebration of the First Anniversary of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights [disc 1 of 4], 12/10/1949; corwin_0277; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Celebration of the First Anniversary of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights [disc 2 of 4], 12/10/1949; corwin_0278; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Celebration of the First Anniversary of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights [disc 3 of 4], 12/10/1949; corwin_0279; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Celebration of the First Anniversary of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights [disc 4 of 4], 12/10/1949; corwin_0280; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - "Susan's Evening", 1964; typed notes; printed program; correspondence; photographs (Box 14)
  - Interviews
    - Norman Corwin, interviewed by Erik Barnouw (189), 1966; transcript of interview recorded for OHRO at Columbia University (Box 14)
    - David Ben-Gurion, interviewed by Norman Corwin (342), 1967; printed material, newspaper clippings with photographs (Box 14)
    - Norman Corwin, interviewed by Harry Kersey, May 3 and 7, 1967; corwin_0369; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 31)
      Label reads: "Harry Kersey, news director of KACL, Santa Barbara, interviews Corwin on May 3, 1967, while latter was Regents Lecturer at the University of California in Santa Barbara. / Reminiscences of SPOON RIVER ANTHOLOGY, among other subjects discussed. / Also THE RIVALRY and THE WORLD OF CARL SANDBURG."
    - Norman Thomas, interviewed by Norman Corwin (375), 1932; typescript (Box 15)
  - Lyrics
    - Cantata, "The Golden Door" (187), 1955; final original typescript, press clippings (photocopies) (Box 15)
    - Oratorio, "The Miracle," music by Lyn Murray (216), 1964; published vocal score (Box 15)
    - Oratorio, "Sleep Now on Thy Natal Day," music by Lyn Murray (179), undated; sheet music; (Box 15)
  - Narrations
    - Cantata, "The Young Wrestler," music by Roy Harris (302), 1965; typescript text of verse, two printed announcements of concert dedicated to Lincoln (Box 15)
    - Oratorio, "The Christmas Story," music by R. Nelson (190), 1965; marked copy of text; associated announcements (Box 15)
    - Oratorio, "Joshua," music by Franz Waxman
      - Publicity (149, 450), 1961; programs, announcements, press reviews, (Box 15)
      - Score (377), published score, signed and inscribed by Waxman; printed program from world premier in Dallas (Box 15)
  - Operas
    - Esther, music by Lyn Murray
      See also Radio programs: Esther.
      - Correspondence, 1941; 1945-1947 (Box 15)
      - Lyrics to "Love" (291), 1943; handwritten page; published sheet music (Box 15)
      - Manuscript (293), 1941 (Box 15)
      - Typescript with composer's notes (292), 1941 (Box 15)
    - The Warrior
      See also Samson.
      Libretto by Corwin, music by Bernard Rogers. This one-act opera was presented by the Metropolitan Opera Company at the Metropolitan Opera House on January 11, 1947. Max Rudolf conducted; Mack Harell sang the role of Samson, and Regina Resnik sang Delilah. Herbert Graf was in charge of stage direction and the set was designed and lit by Samuel Leve. The script is published in the volume MORE BY CORWIN. The libretto was published separately in the GRAND OPERA series, by Fred Rullman, Inc.
      Composer Rogers had earlier requested Corwin’s permission to draft the text of his verse play SAMSON, presented in 1941 an one of the 26 BY CORWIN series over CBS (non-operatic); Corwin did not participate and Rogers used the text almost verbatim. The opera was performed twice by the Met, and was received with hostility by most of the critics. The New Yorker and one or two eastern newspapers were the only exceptions to the generally unfavorable reaction. Prior to its production by the Met, and directly contributory to it, THE WARRIOR was awarded a $1500 first prize as the most meritorious American work submitted in a competition organized by the Ditson Fund of Columbia University. the score was submitted anonymously, under the terms of the competition, and the international jury included Edward Johnson, the General Manager of the Met.
      - The Warrior (Opera) [disc 1 of 3], corwin_0215; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - The Warrior (Opera) [disc 2 of 3], corwin_0216; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - The Warrior (Opera) [disc 3 of 3], corwin_0217; Lacquer discs/acetates
  - Poetry
    - Home for the fourth (328), 6 Jul 1946; published in Collier's magazine, featured on cover; no relation to later broadcast with same title (Oversize 1)
    - Village verse (218), 5 Feb 1967; five limericks published in West magazine, part of the Los Angeles Times; includes published version and several typescripts (Oversize 1)
  - Radio programs, bound compilations
    - Columbia Presents Corwin, 1944, Mar-Aug; bound volume containing typescripts for 22 episodes of the first season of the show, many with annotations, corrections, notes, etc. (Box 16)
      See also specific show titles under Radio programs, individual for related material (correspondence, scripts, recordings, etc.)
      Purchased, 2014.
      Contents:
      Movie Primer, originally aired March 7, 1944, 35pp.
      The Long Name None Could Spell, originally aired March 14, 1944, 27pp; published in More by Corwin: 18 Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1944
      The Lonesome Train, written by Millard Lampell and Earl Robinson, originally aired March 21, 1944, 11pp.
      Savage Encounter, originally aired March 28, 1944, 30pp; published in Untitled and other Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1945
      The Odyssey of Runyon Jones, originally aired April 4, 1944, 32pp., "No corrections."; published in Thirteen by Corwin, Henry Holt 1942
      You Can Dream, Inc., originally aired April 11, 1944, 29pp.; published in Untitled and other Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1945
      Untitled, originally aired April 18, 1944, 21pp.; published in Untitled and other Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1945
      Dorie Got a Medal, originally aired April 25, 1944, 16pp.
      The Cliché expert, originally aired May 2, 1944, 39pp., "Few corrections"
      Cromer, originally aired May 9, 1944, 30pp; published in More by Corwin: 18 Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1944
      New York: A Tapestry for Radio, originally aired May 16, 1944, 23pp "Few corrections"; published in Untitled and other Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1945
      Tel Aviv, originally aired May 23, 1944, 33pp, "With many rewritten passages in pencil in Corwin's hand"; published in Untitled and other Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1945
      Untitled [rebroadcast], originally aired May 30, 1944, 26pp "Few corrections"; published in Untitled and other Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1945
      An American Trilogy - Sandburg, originally aired June 6, 1944, 31pp.
      An American Trilogy - Thomas Wolfe, originally aired June 13, 1944, 19pp.
      An American Trilogy - Walt Whitman, originally aired June 20, 1944, 25pp.
      Home for the Fourth, originally aired July 4, 1944, 28pp.
      The Moat Farm Murders, originally aired July 18, 1944, 32pp; published in Untitled and other Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1945
      El Capitan and the Corporal, originally aired July 25, 1944, 34pp; published in Untitled and other Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1945
      A Pitch to Reluctant Buyers, written by Jerome Lawrence and Robert E. Lee, originally aired August 1, 1944, 29pp.
      A Very Fine Type Girl, originally aired August 8, 1944, 38pp.
      There Will Be Time Later, originally aired August 15, 1944, 34pp; published in Untitled and other Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1945
    - Columbia Presents Corwin, 1945, Jul-Aug; bound volume containing typescripts for 7 episodes of the second season of the show, many with annotations, corrections, notes, etc. (Box 16)
      Unity Fair, originally aired July 3, 1945, 23pp.
      Daybreak [originally in the series 26 by Corwin], originally aired July 10, 1945, 22pp.; published in Thirteen by Corwin, Henry Holt 1942
      The Undecided Molecule, originally aired July 17, 1945, 36pp.; published in Untitled and other Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1945
      New York: A Tapestry for Radio [from 1944 series], originally aired July 24, 1945, 24pp.; published in Untitled and other Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1945
      A Walk with Nick, originally aired July 31, 1945, 31pp.
      Savage Encounter [from 1944 series], originally aired August 7, 1945, 22pp; published in Untitled and other Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1945
      L'affaire Gumpert, originally aired August 21, 1945, 32pp.
    - Two for Everybody, Everywhere, 1945; bound volume containing typescripts for two Corwin productions, with numerous annotations, corrections, notes, etc. (Box 16)
      On a note of triumph, originally aired May 8, 1945, 58pp., "chock full of corrections with not a single page devoid of edits or additions"; published in Untitled and other Radio Dramas, Henry Holt 1945
      Word from the people, originally aired April 24, 1945, 84pp, "includes scattered pencil, pen, and typed editsalong with portions crossed out, running times, and revised pages inserted throughout"
  - Radio programs, individual
    For programs that were part of a series, the series and episode number (if known) are given. Bear in mind that many of Corwin's programs were broadcast more than once.
    Tapes are boxed, discs are shelved individually by ID number. Broken or damaged discs have been rehoused in special boxes. Please request items by ID number.
    - L'Affaire Gumpert (57?), Columbia Presents Corwin, Season 2 #7
      - Recording
        Written expressly for Charles Laughton and Elsa Lanchester, and broadcast over CBS on August 21, 1945, as the seventh program in the second season of COLUMBIA PRESENTS CORWIN. The musical score was composed by Carmen Dragon and conducted by Lud Gluskin. David Frisita performed as the reincarnated Paganini. Corwin's brother Emil played a small role. Unpublished. On the sleeve's label a note indicates that additional data is in envelope 91.
        - Gumpert [disc 1 of 2], August 21, 1945; corwin_0181; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Gumpert [disc 2 of 2], August 21, 1945; corwin_0182; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Script, 1945; final mimeo; also includes correspondence (Box 17)
    - An American in England, radio series transmitted live from England via shortwave, based on Corwin’s trip to England for CBS in 1942
      See also Productions of others: BBC, Sounds of War.
      - Correspondence, clippings, miniature reproductions of scripts (51), 1943 (Box 17)
      - Recording, Episode 5: The Yanks are Here
        Fifth of the AMERICAN IN ENGLAND series written and directed by Corwin. Broadcast from BBC studios in London on August 31, 1942. Musical score composed by Benjamin Britten and performed by the R. A. F. Symphony orchestra. Script unpublished. A handwritten note on side 1 indicates that Ed. Murrow is the producer.
        - The Yanks Are Here Parts 1 and 3 [disc 1 of 4], August 31, 1942; corwin_0146; Shellac disc
        - The Yanks Are Here Parts 2 and 4 [disc 2 of 4], August 31, 1942; corwin_0147; Shellac disc
        - The Yanks Are Here Parts 5 and 7 [disc 3 of 4], August 31, 1942; corwin_0148; Shellac disc
        - The Yanks Are Here Parts 6 and 8 [disc 4 of 4], August 31, 1942; corwin_0149; Shellac disc
      - Recording, Episode 6: An Anglo-American Angle
        Broadcast from Maida Vale studios of BBC, London. Written and directed by Corwin, and produced by Edward R. Murrow in London as the sixth program of the AMERICAN IN ENGLAND series for which Corwin flew to England during the war. The printed date on the sleeve's label is September 8, 1942, but is crossed of with a black marker. On the left side of the label is handwritten different date: Dec. 12. Joseph Julian narrated, and Betty Hardy appeared as Betty. The original score was composed by Benjamin Britten [this sentence is underlined with a blue pencil], and performed by the R.A.F. Symphony orchestra under Wing Commander R. P. O'Donnell. The script is published in UNTITLED AND OTHER RADIO DRAMAS. Atmospheric disturbances garbled short-wave transmission during the original broadcast, and although the program was heard in Britain, it was not heard in the U.S. until Dec. 15 of the same year, when it was produced as part of the extended home-based series. For this production the role of Betty was performed by Edna Best, and music was by Lyn Murray.
        - An Anglo-American Angle (part 1 of 2), Dec 15, 1942; corwin_0142; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 4)
          On the disc label the date is 12/15/1945. The disc is a copy.
        - An Anglo-American Angle (part 2 of 2), Dec 15, 1942; corwin_0143; Lacquer discs/acetates
          The label on to the disc is handwritten. The original disc's label was found in the sleeve of corwin_0140, "Home is Where You Hang Your Helmet". For further information refer to the digital image file of sleeve. The date on the disc's label is 12/15/1945.
      - Recording, Episode 7: Cromer
        Produced on December 1, 1942, as the seventh of the AMERICAN IN ENGLAND series based on Corwin's trip to England for CBS in 1942. Later re-broadcast in May of 1944. Corwin considered this one of the best, if not the best, of the series. Joseph Julian was the Joe who tells the story. Music was composed and conducted by Lyn Murray. The script was later produced in Australia, Canada and Egypt. Characters, names and places in the script are actual, based on Corwin's visit to the town of Cromer in the fall of 1942. Published in MORE BY CORWIN. On the sleeve's label is written that additional data is in envelope 51. Also aired later as Columbia Presents Corwin #10.
        - Cromer [disc 1 of 2], Dec 1, 1942; corwin_0122; Lacquer discs/acetates
          This is a copy. On the disc's label is printed "Part two", but it is crossed off and in pen is written "Part One". Also aired later as Columbia Presents Corwin #10.
        - Cromer [disc 2 of 2], Dec 1, 1942; corwin_0123; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 3)
          This is a copy. On the disc's label is printed "Part one", but it is crossed off and in pen is written "Part Two." Also aired later as Columbia Presents Corwin #10.
        - Cromer [disc 1 of 2], May 9, 1944; corwin_0213; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Cromer [disc 2 of 2], May 9, 1944; corwin_0214; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Recording, Episode 8: Home is Where You Hang Your Helmet
        Produced on December 8, 1942, as the eighth of the AMERICAN IN ENGLAND series, written and directed by the author. Lyn Murray composed and conducted the original score. Joe Julian narrated, and the broadcast originated in New York, as part of the series extended from its original site in London. The script, with notes appended, appears in UNTITLED AND OTHER DRAMAS. Broadcast over the BBC and CBS networks.
        - Home is Where You Hang Your Helmet [disc 1 of 2], Dec 8, 1942; corwin_0140; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 4)
        - Home is Where You Hang Your Helmet [disc 2 of 2], Dec 8, 1942; corwin_0141; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 4)
      - Recording, Episode 10: Clipper Home